Welcome to session eight.
This session is dedicated to the W in
Empower, workforce and leadership.
We'll be exploring the critical link between
effective people management and its
direct impact on business valuation.
We're looking at key challenges in team
leadership, And we're following that with
the introduction of some AI powered
solutions.
These AI tools are designed to help you
build and maintain a high performing
workforce capable of operating
seamlessly with minimal hands-on
supervision.
We are at session 8 of 12, so we're really in
the program's last leg.
We'll have office hours this week with
Hayden on Wednesday, followed by
session 9 next Monday on execution
systems.
I'm going to launch our regular milestone
check-in poll just to see where
everybody's at.
Here we go.
should be seeing that on your screen now.
So again, hoping that you've had the
opportunity to run the lead to sale
assessment and then optional was to
create level one and two SOPs for lead to
sale.
All right.
So I'm sharing the results now.
For folks who haven't yet started, you
know, you're always welcome to post in
circle if you hit a roadblock.
Come to office hours on Wednesday and
we can help you work through any issues
as well as DM Josh Hayden or myself for
some help.
I think we're all very familiar with this
slide by now.
Again, today we're focused on the
enabling process layer.
This is supporting and strengthening the
core of our business, and this is where
workforce and leadership lie.
Our goal today is to build that strong
foundation, ensuring your workforce and
leadership systems are scalable, robust,
and don't rely solely on you.
Today, we'll look at a three-part workforce
transformation framework, all packed
with practical, immediate actions.
The first is leadership structure and
delegation, set in another way.
That is how to distribute decision-making
effectively.
Then we're looking at hiring and
performance management, so how to get
the best people for your organization
hired.
And finally, we're looking at employee
development and retention, so that's how
to invest in your people effectively.
to help them grow while keeping them
engaged in your business.
And with that, I'm going to throw it over
to Hayden.
Thanks, Madhuri.
So as I've looked at a lot of small
businesses, and I'd say that's under 100
employees, most owners actually become
their own bottleneck to growth
inadvertently, often because They
centralize decision-making.
So this is probably the number one thing
is nothing moves without owner approval,
which can create delays.
Again, this is, it sounds like owners are
doing this horrible things.
This is all inadvertent.
It's all part of basically the natural
progression of knowing your business
really well and growing organically.
Often a lot of critical knowledge is also
kind of hoarded in the owner's head.
So that makes the business really
vulnerable when the owner is unavailable.
It also prevents others from making
informed decisions.
Owners can often maintain perfectionist
standards.
I actually don't like the title of that.
I would say that owners will often
continue doing things on their own
because they don't believe anyone else
can do it as well as them.
I think maintaining really strong
standards is a very good and important
thing.
We'll talk quite a bit about that today.
But I think sometimes there's ego
attachments to doing work.
And sometimes there's maybe a lack of
patience or faith in others.
And often that comes because there's a
lack of a delegation framework, right?
So a systematic way to delegate to others,
also to understand that that delegation is
actually a two-way road and that you
actually need to train other people as well
on how to effectively receive delegation,
just because it's not an easy task.
Now, all the businesses that I own have a
leadership team, regardless of their size.
And when we buy a business, most
businesses were typically owner-run, total
owner-operator running it.
And we would usually promote about two
to three people within the business to a
leadership team.
And we'd usually do that within 30 days of
actually buying the business.
And at that point, it would be a trial for a
leadership team.
So you on this call may or may not already
have a leadership team.
If you do, I can share with you sort of my
own requirements for a leadership team.
Let's see if it matches what you're doing.
If you don't, you may want to consider
building a leadership team and happy to
also use the Q&A at the end of the session
to answer any questions about that.
So my requirements, when I ask people to
join a leadership team, I kind of tell them
what the requirements are.
and also tell them sort of what the comp
structure is.
And one of the requirements is I typically
want them to have process ownership.
So I want them to be accountable usually
for a key function in the business.
I want to ensure that they have time to
work on transformational goals, right?
So transformational is different from
operational.
Operational, the way I look at this is like
operational is you set KPIs and you do
work to meet those KPIs.
A transformational goal is doing work on
the side to extend the reach of those or
extend the scope of those KPIs, right?
So operationally as a sales, since we just
did sales, as a sales, in a sales function,
you may have goals to hit certain
conversion rates, to close leads on a
certain cycle, to hit certain pipelines.
A transformational goal in sales would be
creating you know, a better enablement
system that permanently increases your
sales conversion rate goal, right?
So instead of 20%, it becomes 30%, right?
Or to create an AI-based system that
automatically, you know, does a whole
bunch of your lead scoring, right?
And CRM entry.
In a lot of operating systems, those are
called rocks, right?
In Some people may be going by OKRs,
objectives and key results.
But to me, if you're on a leadership team,
you need to be owning those
transformational goals, typically on a
minimum of a quarterly basis.
When we set up a leadership team, we
usually do our rocks on a two-month basis
for the first year and then switch to
quarterly because we want to have a
faster feedback loop because often the
rocks are the wrong rocks when we're first
starting out.
Obviously to do that, you need to have
enough time for actual knowledge work,
right?
So leaders need capacity for strategic
thinking and planning.
If you invite someone on your leadership
team and 90% of their time is doing
operational tasks or joining the leadership
team means you're sacrificing something
really key operationally, right?
If they're your number one salesperson
and their participation in the leadership
team means you are giving up revenue,
That's probably not right.
As part of the leadership team, they
should actively contribute to leadership
meetings and offsites.
So typically, we'll do weekly leadership
meetings.
We'll do quarterly leadership offsites.
They should be bringing insights and
solutions to those meetings.
And that contribution can be actively
adding things proactively, or it can be
reactively.
Business finance literacy is a prerequisite
for me, for a leadership team.
There are certain books that I'll get people
to start reading, but at a very basic, at the
very minimum, they need to understand
how to read P&L statements and how to
understand how their area impacts those
P&L statements.
And then in all of my business,
owner-aligned compensation.
So if I want people to think like owners, I
want to incentivize them and compensate
them as owners.
Usually that is in an EBITDA-based
performance bonus or a profit before
taxes performance-based bonus or
sometimes a pure gross profit percentage
bonus.
I'm happy to answer any questions if
people are curious on how to set that up.
I believe that is more and more important
in the age of AI because as you learn AI, as
your team learns AI, they become
significantly more leveraged
and important to the organization.
And, you know, you want to give people,
you want to incentivize people well to
basically automate out all of their
responsibilities so that they can take on
higher level responsibilities.
And in my opinion, the best way to do that
is to incentivize them as like owners,
right?
So if we grow the business 50% this year,
there's a meaning, you know, your
compensation is also growing 50%.
One of the unique aspects of our
operating system is I ask, I want the
leadership team to be process owners.
And I really like this concept of having
basically each member of a leadership
team represent a key stakeholder in the
organization.
So for example, in our companies, a lot of
them, because they are supply
constrained businesses,
that require people to do work.
We have a people and culture person in
the organization, and they are also on the
leadership team.
And they kind of represent employee
interests for the company, including
training, ongoing training, culture, but
also obviously recruitment and standard
HR things.
Typically, we have someone representing
the ownership and financial stakeholder.
So profitability, sustainability, there's a
natural tension that exists between those
first two, right?
So someone who's representing
employees and culture, there's a natural
tension to say, hey, I want to give people
better insurance, health insurance.
I want to give people better hours.
And then the finance needs to tug on that
and say, well, we need to protect our
profitability.
And so that tension, I think, is healthy.
I typically will have someone in a
customer acquisition role.
So often representing both markets, a
lead and lead to sale on the leadership
team depends on the size of the company.
It's, it's great.
If you're large enough to have one
represent each we can talk about some,
how that handoff works, but this person
represents basically growing revenue in
your organization as well as sort of the
market needs.
Then we'll have someone operationally
who manages typically sale to delivery
and delivery to success, or just calling it
sale to success and fulfillment that
represents quality interests for the
company.
So they would measure customer success,
they would measure NPS, they would
ensure that the products are all rated
highly.
And then finally you have the GM, right?
The general manager or CEO, often this is
you, Maybe if you get to the point where
you are an actual CEO, then it's a GM that
manages this.
But I actually think a GM's role is to very
patiently grow the leadership team, right?
And grow the quality of the leadership
team, but also balance the stakeholder
interests, right?
And make the ultimate decisions between
a lot of the trade-offs that exist.
And obviously grow the leadership team
and how they support the overall strategy
culture and alignment.
Um, if you don't have a large team, uh,
one interesting thing that you can do, and
I've actually seen multiple people do is
create a little AI leadership team, right?
So literally create, uh, create a simple
prompt that basically says you are my
people and culture leader.
This is the, this is the, uh, interests and
stakeholder you represent.
This is your role.
and then give it the context for any
decision you want to make.
You can even have more sophisticated
setups where you have each of these roles
argue with each other about specific
decisions and sort of watch that
conversation evolve, which is quite
fascinating.
This is one of the areas that has probably
the highest AI enablement, in my opinion.
So AI enables, like in the past, many
different frameworks for smaller
businesses that were only available to
larger businesses in the past.
So things like the world's best hiring and
recruiting systems in the form of things
like top grading.
In addition,
A lot of anything that involves sort of
meetings and meeting optimization,
which is a huge part of the culture of a
company can be massively AI assisted.
So, you know, obviously everyone is using
sort of note takers, but are they, you
know, making AI prepare for the meeting
and prepare everyone else for the
meeting?
Are they using actual real-time
facilitation?
which is something that's becoming bigger
nowadays.
Are they actually doing automated
follow-up and accountability
post-meeting, or is it just sending their
standard sort of meeting update and
nobody really looks at it?
AI is also, like I just said in the last slide,
great for decision support systems, right,
by giving Claude certain prompts for
context.
It's extremely good for accountability.
So one of the things that we're doing in
our company is we'll get into sort of the
clarity boards.
And if we have time at the end, I'll actually
share my screen and show some clarity
boards that AI creates.
But it kind of does this like bottoms up
approach to execution.
So one of the things we're doing is
teaching individual contributors how to
have conversations with Claude that then
surface
their own OKRs going forward and even
then structure all of the meetings that
they're having going forward.
So as opposed to us going top down and
doing this, which we had to do in the past,
you can now bring the system and go
bottom up and actually have a lot of the
rock review, rock revision happen on an
individual basis from the bottom up.
Strategic planning, AI is fantastic with as
well.
I'm starting to play with proactive agents
in this area.
I don't have anything I can fully release
yet, but it's super interesting.
And in manager coaching, this happens in
many different ways, but all sorts of
training and onboarding is super, super
helpful with AI.
But also any kind of call review, whether
it's
part of a sales process, whether it's part of
a fulfillment process, AI can automatically
score those calls, can automatically flag
sort of poorly scoring calls for call review,
can flag really high scoring calls for call
review in a group, right?
Which also makes the person who did the
call feel great and then show what good
looks like to everyone else.
Yeah, AI is fantastic for this.
Even just the onboarding piece, like if
there's one piece that you take out of this
whole thing, it would probably be like use
AI to create a full onboarding process for
every single one of your employees, but
turn it into a prompt that actually has
your own employees create it for you.
I can show you more about that at the
end.
Before you get on to the slide, Hayden,
there's a couple of comments in the chat
around AI leaders and whether you give
them an individual personality and
around decision support, if you've ever
experienced wrong support due to invalid
data.
So, for example, a hallucination.
So the first question, do I give them a
personality?
I give them a role and a stakeholder that
they advocate for.
I wouldn't say I necessarily give them a
personality.
But yeah, I think the main thing is giving
them a role, giving them a scope, giving
them an advocate, and then And then
giving them proper context, obviously,
which we're doing with the master
prompt primarily.
Sorry, the second question was?
around decision support if you've ever
experienced wrong support due to invalid
data?
100%, all the time.
That's why taste matters.
That's why the person who's receiving the
support really should know enough about
what makes a good decision.
This is you to the power of AI.
If the you is really, really low, the
exponent is not nearly as valuable.
So if I were to say, I believe the proper role
to receive sort of strategic support like
this is one that should already be giving
the strategic or doing the strategic work.
It's not that you equip someone without
the experience with an AI tutor that tells
them what to do and trust it.
So it's like a challenger.
Exactly, yeah.
It's a challenger.
So what I've found is AI, first of all, saves
you a lot of time, as you've probably
noticed as you go back and forth with
some of these prompts.
The fact that it's asking you questions and
then answering its own questions is
probably revealing a lot more context
than you would normally give if you were
thinking about it on your own.
In addition, You can go back to it with
various frameworks that you'll learn and
basically challenge it to look at everything
through the lens of this framework.
And it will fully give you all of that,
unleash all of that potential, which, again,
us humans are not nearly as capable of
doing.
And it also, if those lenses are designed to
create insights and innovations, it will
surface them.
And again, those are things that, you
know, if you were given a very specific
context and scope to look at, you probably
would have figured out on your own.
But it would have taken you quite a bit of
time and you would have had to go
through that scope.
But AI is able to just surface it all.
But you get out what you put in.
It's kind of the key to this all.
And so I think the whole, I think the
innovation of the master prompt is a
combination of like the context is always
there.
So you're always putting the context in,
but it's also that it's asking questions to
the right user and answering its own
questions about the user and allowing the
user to kind of expand upon that context.
And that's what kind of creates like really
strong context into whatever you're trying
to create.
Go ahead, Don.
I think you're muted.
Yeah.
Okay.
I'm back.
Hello.
Hi, Hayden.
Great topics today, as usual.
I would love for you to maybe give me
some examples of specific ideas around
the leadership-based, or rather around
the owner-aligned compensation.
That's what I'm after.
The owner-aligned compensation, because
it does certainly create...
A lot of owners are into transparency and
I'm sure you deal with stuff like that.
And any comments you have about your
experiences actually implementing this
stuff would be great.
Yep.
So a lot of it will depend on the industry
context.
And I would say also the maturity of the
industry in anything that isn't, let's say
like startup Silicon Valley style
environment.
I would say that, most people value cash
over equity.
And you as an owner, cash is much
cheaper than equity.
And so you also value cash over equity.
So again, if you come from a more mature
startup environment, that may not be the
case.
And then you may need to be looking into
stock option pools and stuff like that.
I'm going to assume that you don't.
It's construction.
I'm talking construction.
Yeah, so-
Yeah, my game there, yeah.
So cash first, cash-based compensation.
I like to give people a percentage of
EBITDA growth, right?
Sometimes you give it over a baseline.
So let's say this last year you did a million
dollars in EBITDA, you might give them a
percentage EBITDA growth over 10%,
right?
So anything over 1.1, I will give them a
percentage of growth.
I like to give the full leadership team a
percent, right?
Typically...
15 to 20% over that baseline, maybe 20%
over that baseline.
And I like to split it up and leaving a
section unallocated for future potential
members of leadership team.
I like to keep the bonus stuck to a single
baseline.
So if I start year one and it's at a million
dollars and I say that the expected CAGR
of this business is 10%,
And year two, I'm giving the bonus on
anything over 1.1.
Year three, I'd give the bonus on anything
over 1.2-ish, a little bit more, because of
the compound effect.
That acts as golden handcuffs, assuming
that you actually have year-over-year
growth.
Because if you get to the point where
you're making over three years, you're
making $2 million now in EBITDA, you're
still getting paid on an EBITDA over 1 point
something.
at that point.
Quitting means giving up a very, very large
bonus.
There are other pieces of this, but yeah,
typically for like a construction business,
it's cash-based, it's EBITDA based.
Often year one, it'll be gross profit based
because they don't actually have control
over EBITDA.
And there may be some larger expenses
you wanna put in.
That's up to you though.
And how often do you do the calculation
and pay the bonuses?
So pay the bonus quarterly, usually.
And if you have a down quarter, you need
to obviously adjust for that accordingly.
And very important, going back to our
finance framework, you only pay the
bonus out if you have a certain number of
months of OpEx or burn in the bank, right?
And everyone needs to know that upfront.
Very, very important.
And there should always be a mechanism
to claw back if you have a down quarter.
Okay.
Makes sense.
Great.
Voice of experience.
Yeah.
I mean, I also am really interested in
ESOPs as like a way for companies to get
liquidity, especially in the US.
So, you know, if you're ever interested in
that and want to see like what great really
looks like from this perspective, there's
the great game of business, which is a
book,
written years ago by a guy who formed an
ESOP for a remanufacturing company,
does workshops and company tours,
which are really quite amazing.
Something I would check out if I were you.
I think they have this ridiculous stat.
I think they formed as an ESOP 40 years
ago, and they've had 40 years of
successive growth and have grown
something like multiples ahead.
I can't remember the exact number, but
something like 25X Berkshire Hathaway as
a company.
Really fascinating.
Wonderful.
Okay, thank you.
One thing that I've been working on a lot
over the last several months is this idea of
building a business brain.
And building a business brain is effectively
like it works from the bottom up.
So teaching all of your team AI and having
AI interview your team in order to actually
understand process ownership from the
bottom up is actually, I've found a much
more effective way to do this than going
top down.
So as you graduate this cohort, you
probably have core processes, maybe
some blueprints laid out.
And you may be thinking, OK, now I need
to teach, do this myself or teach this
myself.
I personally think that's the wrong
approach.
And the right approach is actually
teaching your team how to uncover a lot
of this from the bottom up and then build
up a bit of a business brain so that you can
surface a bunch of, ideas Process
ownership gaps, delegation opportunities,
responsibility, distribution, et cetera.
Again, happy to answer questions.
That's a very large topic.
But this is where I see some of the most
use is teaching your team how to use AI,
almost having them go through a similar
program in order to surface all of this.
I have, so I created, my job descriptions
always looked like roles are a collection of
responsibilities which are tied to
processes which have success metrics,
which I think is a little bit more thorough
than how most people approach a role.
Most people will approach a role as a role
has a job description and maybe people
have five to seven The next level up might
be that people have five to seven KPIs in a
role.
And the next level up above that might be
that they have outcomes defined on a
monthly basis.
But I kind of do look at this as holistically
as your role as a collection of
responsibilities that are tied to the
processes that you are responsible,
accountable, consulted for, that then each
of those processes have success metrics.
It's an interesting distinction.
Because it also means that as your team,
you and your team are able to automate
functions within processes, roles evolve
rapidly, right?
So I think, I personally think like this is the
last year you'll ever see like a single like
CMO style role simply because so much of
that role, so many pieces of that process
are being automated by AI that that role,
know couldn't possibly have more in a
proper functioning company probably
shouldn't be spending more than five
hours a week on, right.
Maybe 10 hours a week on.
So now you might see you have a lot more
chief revenue officers in smaller
companies that handle both, you know,
marketing and sales leadership and a
finance function, right.
Without having those other rules beneath
them.
Um, simply because as i said, processes
become more automated, um, those
responsibilities, um,
require less human hours for the same
output.
And so roles end up evolving into much
broader roles.
And I think we're seeing that already in
programming as programmers.
So the junior programmer role is
disappearing.
In some ways, the product manager role is
actually evolving into what would have
been maybe four or five different roles
where you had a product manager, you
had, you know, maybe one or two senior
developers and two junior developers.
That's all turning into one role, which is
effectively like a product manager that's
responsible for, you know, speccing,
prototyping, giving feedback and
potentially even, you know, determining
feasibility.
I'm going to pause there for a second.
Does anyone have any questions related
to this slide or the last?
So some context on the idea of a clarity
board.
I remember an early mentor taught me
like a very simple way of looking at
business was clarity, right?
So if everyone in the company knows
where the company is going, has clarity in
where the company is going, if everyone in
the company has clarity in their role in
getting there, and if everyone in the
company has clarity
clarity in how success in that role is
measured, everybody has clarity, those
simple three things.
And so I initially created Clarity Awards to
try to help achieve that for everyone.
And they were originally designed by a
people and culture manager with the
individual employees.
And they acted as like, we did them in
Google Sheets originally.
They acted as like a one-stop shop for
everything that employees needed.
So it included obviously their role
responsibilities, links to all their
processes, links to their scorecards and
expected outcomes, links, if they had
them, links to their ROCs or OKRs.
It had like their personal meeting
schedule and communication cadences,
the agendas for all their meetings, had the
full, you know, links to the employee
handbooks, mission vision values, core
values, et cetera.
Even had all their onboarding together.
So initially we did this in, in,
Coda, which was like a Notion competitor
years ago, and then we did it in Google
Sheets, and now we are just custom
making them with AI.
So before, we had an entire role that
designed these things, and it took quite a
bit of time to do them.
Today, it's now a single prompt that
designs them in basically working in
conjunction with the actual employee.
I will share an example of ClarityBoard,
and I can share an example of the prompt
as well if people are interested to do it at
the end of the session.
Okay, next part is hiring and performance
management.
Obviously we went over quite a bit.
This is a very dense session.
So if anyone has any questions right now,
please feel free to ask.
There's definitely interest in seeing an
example clarity board at the end of the
session.
Okay, so part of the AI first culture shift.
So AI enables both faster and higher
quality work, which means it needs to go
in combination with reset expectations for
both speed and quality.
If you don't have, if you don't raise those
bars, that's why a lot of implementations
and organizations don't work.
Because people end up using AI,
automating certain things, and then just
kind of resting on their laurels.
So this does need to come with higher
expectations.
AI is also excellent at creating
accountability and becoming an
accountability partner.
If you are like me, I hate cracking the
whip.
terrible at it.
AI is an incredible and friendly nudger of
everyone on your team if you set it up to
do that.
And then the other thing I would say is
like part of the AI first culture shift needs
to be recognizing achievement within the
team and just having, I would say, a
general culture of like,
recognition around experimentation and
playfulness, because those are actually
the traits of people that succeed with AI,
as people who are curious, who are willing
to experiment and are willing to dig deep
in figuring things out.
We'll talk a bit in a future session on how
to build out and get team buy-in and how
to announce AI and all these other things,
but I wanted to mention that this is a key
piece to introducing AI is you need to have
these resets expectations.
So one thing that I'm sure everyone's
heard and probably everyone realizes they
should do, and not a lot of people do, is to
hire slow and fire fast.
In fact, I would almost say that if I look at,
say, acquisition entrepreneurs who buy
businesses, the number one, probably the
number one criteria
for whether or not they'll succeed is their
ability to fire fast and not sit back with
someone who is clearly not a good culture
fit for months on end.
So the key thing here is to, so the key
thing around hiring, around firing fast is
to have clear standards, right?
So nothing unambiguous is to be able to
document issues as they come up, to be
able to coach people.
So coach people as issues come up and
coach them towards success or, you know,
get rid of them.
and part of getting rid of them is using AI
to coach for some of these difficult
conversations.
And so one thing I would look at here is, as
individual owners, how can I use AI to help
me fire fast?
That may not sound like the most fun,
pleasant, and way to look at this, but it is
highly correlated with success, which is
why I mentioned it here.
wanted to take some time we're a small
group, so I think we can just stay here um.
How many people are we sorry.
I think we've got 10.
Okay, maybe make like two to three
groups on yeah um.
yeah just separate and say what's one
performance conversation, you need to
have right now.
As a as a talking point you can.
also talk about if there's nothing you can
think of there on what sort of one way
you'd love to work with AI in sort of
workforce and leadership management.
All right, I am opening all of the rooms and
you don't have to worry about keeping an
eye on time.
We'll do that for you and you'll come right
back to the main room after about 10
minutes.
Welcome back.
Hope folks had fruitful discussions.
Would anyone like to share any of their
discussions?
I could share a quick, um, we ended up
discussing how, how, how in both cases,
like implementing with your team and,
and maybe it's good for you to say
something because like, I feel this is my
second time through the cohort and I'm
taking a pretty different approach to not
doing so much of myself because I know I
want my team to help do the assessments
and I want to have that done before I put
them over into stage three.
And, um,
you know, I probably ended up with about
150 pages worth of documents from the
first cohort that I'm glad I did it.
Don't want to do it again like that.
So yeah, maybe you can just sort of say a
little, I know we're coming up later, but
that was how ours, that's what we ended
up discussing to not get burned out by
people who are trying to go through the
course and also share with their team
alongside.
Yep.
So what I, The way I approach this is I
typically will do the first three sessions.
They're done in a week, kind of giving the,
they're fairly similar to the first three
sessions of this cohort in terms of just
giving people the foundation, the shared
language around a lot of different things.
So stuff around like levels of process,
types of process, et cetera.
The What we do for like sessions four to
nine in the Teams program is that they're
asynchronous and they're much deeper
and related only to the functions that the
employee work in.
So if they work in fulfillment, if they work
in sales, if they work in procurement, they
work in finance, they work in HR, it's
different sessions.
And basically they learn how to create by
going back and forth in conversations with
Claude, they create their own processes.
And like the culmination of that happens.
in the next session, which is the clarity
board, which is the thing I'll share here,
which is basically taking, so it creates this
role master prompt for each individual
employee in addition to the company
master prompt, which exists in the
project.
And then based on this, it helps create a
clarity board.
And then that clarity board surfaces all of
these opportunities and commitments for
them to go out and create their own
process.
So that's my approach is we go bottoms
up, right?
Teach people the fundamentals and then
have them
basically surface up the opportunities and
commit to doing the opportunities.
Then that kind of culminates into a, let's
take the collective intelligence of all the
people that went through that and
compare it to what you did, right?
And then from there, it surfaces gaps and
discrepancies and divergences from what
you understood the processes to be and
what the actual people doing the
processes understand them to be.
And then it now has Everyone has the
ability to use stage three and build out
those processes.
You don't have to do it.
And so it kind of takes the onus off of you
because you're probably already the
bottleneck in a bunch of different areas.
We don't need to add it.
You as the bottleneck in AI and process
creation as well.
But that's sort of the design bottoms up.
Just seeing a comment from Tim as well
that, Nancy, you gave some really good
recommendations on how to delegate
certain tasks and assessments to
colleagues and doing feedback loops.
Okay, so going back to this concept of
performance standards, probably
everyone's familiar with this concept of
Parkinson's law that a task takes as long
as you allocate to it, right?
And so often that's where a lot of
procrastination can come from and busy
work can come from.
With that updated standards, productivity
gains will not be, will not reach the
company.
And so these are, this is like a simple table
of like, I actually would update this table,
but this is sort of the AI multiple.
So content creation is three and a half X
faster.
Therefore your standards need to be
higher.
Ideally three and a half X higher.
I would update this to probably being
more like 10 to 15 now.
Research analysis.
Again, multiple times higher
documentation, multiple times higher
communication, multiple times higher.
So how do you if this is truly the case, how
do you update your standards and how
does that happen over time?
The other interesting question, I call it like
AI arbitrage.
So it's like a framework for actually
saying, if I found something in my
business that AI cuts the cost down
substantially, right?
Rather than just saying, oh, content
creation has dropped 10 X, right?
And so therefore my existing content
creation, which I do four videos a month
now costs me, you know, $2,000 less per
month.
That's sort of the first phase of thinking.
The second phase of thinking, if you see
the giant cost reduction, is what's the
upper level of actual content creation in
your business that doesn't provide
diminishing returns?
And so that's the next level up.
It's like, oh, I make four videos now, but
actually I could make 20 videos a month
and send it to my customer list and
publish it to my YouTube channel without
seeing many diminishing returns.
And then the third question is, what is the
actual max surplus?
And then how do you distribute that
surplus?
So as an example, with content creation,
maybe my max surplus, I've actually, in
one of our businesses, we've dropped
content creation from what was a
probably $3,000 three week per video
down to about $200 one day per video.
And we kind of looked at that and said,
okay, one person could actually create
something like 80 videos a month, right?
But all we can really do on a single
YouTube channel and a single email list is
probably 20.
So how do we identify the surplus for
those 60?
Well, we could, so you basically look at,
am I hitting new markets or am I
reactivating old markets, right?
And then you could say, I'm gonna look at
segments.
Instead of creating a generic video,
Um, let's say for AI enablement, I could
create AI enablement for, uh, construction
companies, videos, or AI enabled and
entirely different AI enablement for
construction companies channels.
Right.
Uh, if I knew segments of my customers,
um, or I knew, uh, segments of my leads
by objection, I could create entire videos
around objections and reach out to my
customers.
And if I know there's ROI there, then I
need to say, okay, I have a plan.
I've cut costs down, you know, by 15 X,
and I have a plan to get to step two within
30 days or 60 days.
Right.
And do 20 videos a month.
And then I have a plan to hit step three,
which is this allocation of cost surplus,
um, within 90 days.
And my new standard is going to go from
two to 80.
Right.
And that can happen with anything.
That can happen with each of these
elements, right?
And these are actually the elements that
AI is probably best at, right?
It's production of content in any of its
forms.
It's research analysis.
It's documentation, which is really
content creation.
And it's communication, which is also
In one of my businesses, same concept, we
were looking at basically creating videos
for our lead lists that had So basically we
had leads of buyers based on state and we
realized we could just enable one person
on our team with cloud code to create
videos, custom videos for each person
based on state and like 10X our
conversion rates in that outreach.
And because our cost and creation of that
video was like down to $200, it was
actually worth doing it to distribute to
under a thousand customers, right?
It's still super high ROI.
So same kind of concept.
Okay, so in the performance management
side, typically in most companies, your
regular performance meetings are in the
form of one-on-ones, which happen either
weekly, biweekly, or monthly, depending
on the business.
Performance reviews, which happen
either quarterly, semi-annually, or
annually, depending on the business.
And then sort of performance and
compensation calibration, which should
happen ideally annually in most
businesses.
Obviously, AI can help you with all of
these.
If you don't currently have structured
versions of these, and you don't currently
actually do quarterly or semiannual
performance reviews, I would highly,
highly suggest you work with AI, which
already knows all your core values, which
already knows everything about your
company, and just ask you to help me
with my performance review structure.
Ask me to help with the performance
review for Joe John Smith.
And just schedule it.
It's really worth doing.
And it cuts the preparation down
massively.
And this is something that often people
kind of dread doing.
So if you can cut the time of dread, it
takes down the probability of it
happening.
It goes way up.
Performance documentation is another
area that most small businesses do not
actually manage, partially because it's a
bunch of work to even set up the
documentation in the first place.
With AI, it's a single 20-minute
conversation with an output.
So first of all, we need to start with
performance standards on roles.
So everyone needs to know what success
looks like in their role.
That's probably the number one most
important thing.
I personally like the top grading approach.
which suggests what success looks like in
outcomes each month for the next three
months, right?
So that's very, very clear and
unambiguous to say that, you know, as of
March, I expect this X, Y, and Z in these
metrics, as of April, X, Y, and Z of these
metrics, as of May, X, Y, and Z, and we will
review again at the end of May.
Secondly, I,
Performance, so PIPS, performance
improvement plans.
This can be built in 15 minutes with
Claude.
If you don't currently have one, just same
idea, ask it to ask you questions and then
build me a performance improvement
plan that matches my core values.
And it aligns to the key metrics in the
business.
Just note that if you make this, if you
don't have this, It's very difficult to
actually enforce accountability.
If you have this and you don't use it, it's
actually worse than not having it because
people then basically see that even
though the system exists, there's no
repercussion.
So if you choose to make this, I think it's
really important that you follow it.
And then everything else on performance
documentation goes down to some of
those performance reviews.
And again, I highly recommend you have
AI help you with your performance review
structure.
Try to have it create objective scoring,
where people do self-scoring beforehand.
And so if you're objectively self-scoring
one to five across various criteria, have AI
create the examples of what one, two,
three, four, and five looks like for every
given role.
Again, that wouldn't have been possible
before AI.
And now it's a matter of a simple
five-minute conversation.
Most people, so management is the next
piece here.
Most people quit their jobs because of bad
managers.
AI can make people way, way better
managers and can especially make first
time, like bring first time managers up to
speed a lot quicker.
So one of these elements is just teaching
managers how to use AI as a coach on how
to deliver effective feedback to their
reports, right?
So literally, if you feel...
Before just reaching out and blurting
something out to somebody and giving
feedback, critical feedback, ask AI how to
give this feedback, right?
And everyone here should do this as well.
I do this constantly, right?
Because I'm not nearly as...
diplomatic and tactful as AI.
And sometimes AI will point out that this
is my problem, not theirs.
This was a lack of, this is poor delegation
on my part, right?
Or this was a lack of delivering what
success looks like.
Obviously documentation standards are
much faster to create with AI.
Performance coaching.
So actually in your PIP, actually coaching
people to improvement, a lot easier to do
with AI, a lot easier to outline with AI on a
custom role by role basis.
And then analysis.
Like I will often take calls that I have.
I might take a one-on-one call Right.
And, you know, put put it in to Claude and
basically ask, you know, how did I do in
this call as a manager?
What could I have done better?
Right.
Again, if that becomes second nature to
people, they will become better managers.
Right.
Over time.
So individual accountability systems,
again, this kind of ties into the clarity
board.
So I always want to have individual
success metrics tied directly back to the
company scorecard metrics.
Even if they are different metrics, they
need to understand what company
scorecard metrics they relate to and how.
So remember that where's the company
going, clarity in where the company is
going, clarity in how my role helps it get
there, and then clarity in how success is
measured.
Um, performance-based compensation is
a huge, I think a huge part of, uh,
business.
And so if you're currently have people on,
you know, on basis without variable, uh, I
would, I would immediately start talking
to AI about how can I create a incentive
plan for this role?
Um, that, you know, only pays them more
as we, as a company succeed, uh, it'll get
very specific.
And then career development integration
is also key.
So having an actual sort of development
plan.
So Don, if you're in construction, one of
the things that we do when we buy a
company is we actually create a
development plan that basically sets like,
you know, rough in level one, rough in
level two, rough in level three, that each
correspond with like, you know, hourly
increases of maybe a dollar or 50 cents so
that people understand that there is an
actual progression.
And that pay is not based on whether the
owner likes you or not.
It's based on merit.
And again, that's something that AI can
set up for you.
So in terms of performance, like under
performance management, so through the
use of a PIP, performance improvement
plan, just remember that the goal is
actually improvement first.
It's not, I'm going to put you on a PIP so I
can fire you and it's been documented.
The goal is improvement first and then
termination only when improvement fails.
The main key here is like your
understanding that if you're not avoiding
an uncomfortable conversation and
dragging out the process, When someone's
on a PIP, you set a very clear timeline and
very clear metrics on what improvement
looks like with their expectations and
support and stick to it.
And so typically, if you do a good job in
performance improvements, most of the
time you do actually are able to coach
people out or coach people up rather than
coaching them out.
But it's only if you actually put in the
effort and again, It can be a single AI
prompt that literally you could screenshot
the slide and say, X person is being put on
a performance improvement plan.
Set this up for me for the next 30, 60, 90.
And like, it's done.
And by the way, the reason some of these
presentations and calls are so dense is so
that you actually do do this.
They're able to kind of look at it and
return back to it and work with Claude
through a lot of it.
So we're on part three.
We're a little behind it.
Are there any questions right now or?
I don't see any questions related to this
last portion.
So this is reiterating some of the things in
the previous slide.
So basically, it's typically poor managers
that people quit due to, or a career ceiling
and development stagnation.
Nice thing about AI is that for people who
are motivated by mastery and by learning,
the pace of learning has never been
anywhere near what it's at today.
And their roles are likely going to change
and evolve.
Um, Some things that you can do
proactively.
Again, typically these are systems
reserved for larger companies.
Most smaller companies don't have the
resources to do it.
And so because of that, basically people
just quit and it seems unexpected and
now they have to rush to hire.
What larger companies will do and what
AI can allow you to do are simple monthly
pulse surveys.
stay interviews, all with the ideal effect of
actually identifying engagement risks
before they actually become retention
issues.
So you look at it as preventative
maintenance.
So I think the easiest thing here to set up,
again, single prompt with Claude is a pulse
survey, right?
Anonymous.
You can make it anonymous.
You can just track engagement scores.
You can track manager ratings.
You can track growth satisfaction.
Um, you can track how appreciative
people feel.
Um, all of that is super useful.
Um, and again, with AI, it's a 30 minute
task.
Um, The one thing I think that AI is
exceptionally good at is actually
personalized recognition.
So recognition is like it's the tool that
costs absolutely nothing, but makes
people just provide such like job
satisfaction.
And so if you are not naturally good at
recognition, asking AI and building it into
your processes to allow managers to
provide recognition
is extremely effective and like infinite ROI
because it costs nothing.
This could be as simple as having
recognition built into every single
meeting, right?
Whether that's a one-on-one, whether
that's like a town hall or all hands,
whether those are standups, it could be
based on any regularly sort of recurring
reports that go into manager's hands to
come up with recognition possibilities.
So the manager does it every single time.
Again, if everyone could be recognized for
something that they did well, whether
that's performing well in their job or
learning or curiosity or taking a shot, the
business becomes a lot more fun place to
work.
So some recognition systems you can
build in beyond your core values.
So in case you don't have it, core values
are probably the first place to look, right?
Because not only does it give recognition,
it also reinforces the core values and sort
of the personality of the company.
Obviously, achievement is a big one.
Peer recognition is a big one.
Build it into processes where peers can
recognize each other.
Learning recognition and process
improvement or creative solution.
or just taking a shot on something is
something I try to recognize.
Again, just understanding that if everyone
were to take more shots, the company
would likely do much better.
So what are the things that if everyone did
it, the company would be way better?
Recognize them.
And again, build it into your systems, your
frequently recurring processes and
systems such that managers identify the
recognition and almost automatically, not
necessarily automatically, but are
reminded of it and give it out.
And that turns into a nice flywheel.
Okay, so in terms of development, some
things that I would recommend you use AI
for are like career progression charts.
Again, simple, that's just a new chat that
you can add and say, help me create a
career progression chart for this role.
First-time manager training.
So I have a couple different books that we
always recommend people read.
Radical Candor is a personal favorite of
mine.
Um, but you also might want to even just
create your own sort of management
training, uh, with AI, um, that people can
go through.
I continuing education is something I try
to put.
So voracious learning is one of the core
values in every single one of my
businesses.
Um, and so including things like book
clubs, including AI training programs,
always having basically a training program
that's optional, um, within the company
that people can join.
I find is extremely important.
You can do that on, people can do it on
their own time if you make it optional.
I probably, you know, in one of my
companies, we've probably done
something like read about 30 or 40 books
together over the course of like five years,
the last five years, as well as gone through
probably about 30 sessions of AI training.
So you can imagine that that compounds a
lot.
A lot of successful companies I've seen
also do community and volunteering
work.
So that can be paid or unpaid and
optional.
But I found that that's especially that's
part of your identity and your core values.
That's something that makes the company
a much better place to work and gives
people pride.
So the management is a very different
skill set from being a strong technical
worker or individual contributor.
And so just something that I'm sure
everyone's aware of, but it bears
reminding.
You need to develop management skills in
people before promoting them.
That is not something that happens
overnight.
I think that's something that should be
understood at least a couple of months in
advance.
You need to separate technical excellence
from management capability in your
evaluation and promotion criteria.
The absolute worst case scenario, which
happens every day, is that you basically
promote a strong individual contributor
who's a poor manager and end up having
one fewer strong individual contributor
and one more incompetent manager.
So just make sure to look out for this.
And again, on the manager training side,
this is something that AI can help with
quite a bit, both for preparing and for the
first month or two in management.
In terms of AI leverage, again, this is more
of a slide for everyone to review on their
own afterwards, but these are all areas
that AI absolutely excels in.
So personalized development, so growth
plans for every single person on an
individual basis that aligns with their
current skills, career aspirations, as well
as your organizational needs.
Again, one of the things that we look at is
building a role master prompt for each
person so that AI understands each
person's role really well.
And so we usually do that as part of the
personal preferences within cloud settings
and then have the master prompt as part
of the project that they work in.
That way, every single employee has
context for both their role and the
company.
Engagement analysis.
So predicting retention issues.
Again, this is something that probably
requires a bit more AI integration
throughout your organization, but I've,
and I personally am not doing this,
Um, but it's something that I've seen
other companies do and talk about.
Um, onboarding automation is a big, big,
big one.
Uh, so personalized learning paths for new
hires.
Like there's no excuse now to not have
any, like just an incredible onboarding
plan that, you know, goes over the first 30
days and has, you know, 10 touch points
with four different people and, you know,
three different mediums.
Right.
That's typically our, our minimum
expectation now on onboarding.
Um, Performance coaching, skills gap
analysis, also great simple things that AI
can help with.
So again, in terms of the requirements for
the AI era, this is what you're going to, as
you build AI and build your teams out and
adopt your teams into using AI, this
concept of dynamic job descriptions needs
to be communicated.
That what your job is today is going to, the
idea here is that we are able to identify
pieces of processes that you're involved in
and automate them, delegate them,
eliminate them.
in order for you to then take on higher
leverage work that is also enabled by AI.
And so what that means is that honestly,
a job description today probably needs to
be reviewed every other month in a truly
sort of AI adopted organization as people
basically replace their low leverage tasks
with higher leverage tasks.
Along with that comes evolving
performance standards, right?
Again, if we drop the cost of something, By
10x, how do we increase the output of it
10x without diminishing returns?
And how does that turn into a
performance standard?
That's what transforms an organization.
AI-aware career progression.
So how do we, I look at this as typically
when you train teams, there are phases.
The first phase is from the bottom up.
using AI on a day-to-day basis to automate
a lot of what you're already doing.
As you train your team, you'll notice that
certain people thrive and certain people,
again, it's typically people who are
curious, relatively confident with
technology, but not necessarily like a
developer, somewhat obsessive.
Those people really thrive in being able to
create workflows and pipelines and And
so the next phase is to eventually get
them into helping cross-functionally, to
helping other people on the team with
those things.
And then the final phase is this AI
operator role, which we have at all our
companies.
And it's, I believe, going to be a primary
important role for every single company
in the future, which is kind of the
architect of much of these systems for AI.
And then compensation systems, I really
believe need to reflect the scale of value
creation patterns and the scale of a single
individual AI operator.
The reality here is that if this doesn't
happen, people who become way more
leveraged in their work will just quit and
they'll become entrepreneurs because
they can.
And they can now do the work of, 10
different people in their company.
The way to kind of overcome that is to
obviously have the organization be a fun
place to work and collaborate in, but also
give them a lot of autonomy and a almost
endless path of career progression and
compensation.
So I really do believe anyone who does this
and fully AI enables their people without
doing this value-based compensation
piece will probably risk
the flight of the vast majority of those
people We have one comment in the chat
from Tim.
Is there also a team master prompt
regarding the team slash department area
besides the master prompt for the whole
company?
So there's an individual master prompt for
each role.
That's basically each person in the
company.
There's no separate master prompt for a
department, if that's the question.
If you wanted to do that in a department, I
think the right way to do that is to do it as
a skill in Cloud as opposed to part of the
master prompt.
Any, so we only have five minutes here.
So I probably will skip a few of these slides
here as we, it's mainly recapping.
Any questions?
Hey, Naito, I just have more general
questions, like if there's more details on
how you do the onboarding from a
bottom-up perspective, which tools you
use, and kind of aligned with that, you had
mentioned this business brain, and I
haven't used Notebook LLM or LM much,
but wondering when you think about
where to store knowledge as a business, is
it in databases or is it in something like
Notebook LM or
and then accessing it through Cloud.
So I just wonder if you have any
recommendations regarding how to use
tools to accomplish any of these things.
Yeah, so I personally am not a huge fan of
Notebook LM.
It has really good, it's really strong at like
very, very specific use cases, but it's
actually surprisingly weak at like actual
organizational use cases.
As an example, despite it being a Google
product, if you put a Google Drive, like a
Google Doc as a source, it does not
dynamically update that source based on
the Google Doc updating.
Yet Claude does, which is odd.
So to answer the question, I think it's very
important that you have a single system
of record that holds your truth.
So in my case, in my companies, I use
stage three as the system of record.
You need two things.
You need a single system of record, and
then you need a synchronization layer
across.
So in my case, I use stage three as the
system of record.
And then I synchronize.
Most of my AI operators use Cloud Code.
And so I synchronize stage three with
Cloud Code to make sure that everyone
stays up to date.
You could do the same thing with Airtable,
with Notion.
Those are common systems of record.
But the key there is to make sure you also
have the synchronization layer, because
you need to be able to keep your master
prompts up to date across all platforms.
And does that include items within your
business that may be very industry
specific that aren't specifically related to
SOPs?
So when I think of a brain for the business,
it may include a lot of technical reference
materials.
that we would want to be able to access
easily within AI, but not have them, but
just where to store those.
Would you store things like that in state
three at some point?
Yes, you can either store it in state.
So if you're using Claude, you can store
that in your master prompt or you can
store it as a skill, right?
So if you go to your settings and you go to
capabilities, you can add skills and there's
a way to add a skill by just having Claude
interview you and it creates the skill.
Right.
And so then the idea of a skill is it's not
being added into your context unless it's
being called.
And Claude knows when to call it.
Right.
So if there's something in your industry
around what's your industry?
Commercial landscaping.
So it might be irrigation.
Yeah.
So if you have like an irrigation guide or
something like irrigation book, playbook
or whatever, you could create as a skill.
And then Claude would know to look it up
every time irrigation is mentioned.
Right.
Or every time you tell it to look up the
skill.
That's probably the easiest.
More than thinking of a library of
materials from all sorts of places,
consolidating that into what's most
relevant to our business and then saving
that as a skill.
Yeah.
So the next step for a lot of people will be
to figure out, okay, what stays in the
master prompt?
What goes in as skills?
And then how do I share this with my
team?
So that's going to be like the session 11
and 12 stuff.
Okay.
So things like skills, though, you would
anticipate sharing and keeping those up
to date in Stage 3 as well, potentially?
Yep.
Again, depending on what tools you're
using, skills themselves are a Cloud
function.
And so you'd want to share the skills in
Cloud with your team.
MasterPrompt has its own knowledge
document version of that.
Sorry, Stage 3 has its own.
So you might have versions and like
managing those versions.
Would you potentially do that in
something like stage three then?
Yeah.
Yep.
Alternatively, you could come up with a
Google drive structure.
You can come up with a GitHub structure.
Those are probably currently where I just
made in the same, same page.
I have archived, you know, versions.
Yep.
Aiden, do you want to throw the slides
back up for a moment and I'll just run
through next steps?
Sure.
And I know you had mentioned a Clarity
Board example.
Does that make sense to throw up as a
post in circle?
Yeah, I have it open right here.
But yeah, I can put this as a post in circle.
And this is actually part of the team
session.
I can probably just share that session if
people are curious.
But basically, this is like an HTML
document that
gets created based on an interview with
each employee.
And so it sort of creates a KPI scorecard.
It creates sort of all of their meetings in
one place, all of their process
involvements, all of their sort of large
automation outcomes that they could
build, an implementation roadmap, and
onboarding.
So again, it's all based on one
conversation, one prompt.
Pretty useful.
And I typically have people do this like
every other month in my companies.
but I'll share this on Circle.
Okay, so between now and next Monday,
you'll be running the Workforce and
Leadership Diagnostic to identify your
biggest opportunities for organizational
effectiveness, employee engagement,
leadership development, and systematic
delegation.
You have the option to create Level 1 and
Level 2 SOPs, as well as explore an AI
hiring protocol.
which is incredibly valuable.
Our next session is Wednesday.
We have office hours.
This week, they're going to be at 4 p.m.
Eastern time.
So please note the change in hours for this
week.
And then we follow up with our ninth
session on Monday, March the 2nd at 1
p.m., where we'll be discussing execution
systems.
Thank you, everybody, for joining us
today.
So great to see you all and get your
questions.
Thanks.
Bye.
Thanks, everyone.
See you on Wednesday.
Bye.
Thanks.
Bye-bye.